<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An examination of Dr. Sherlock's book entituled, The case of the allegiance due to sovereign powers, stated and resolved, &amp;c. by James Parkinson ...</title>
            <author>Parkinson, James, 1653-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56410</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P493</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14794</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13026407</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13026407</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96693</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56410)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96693)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 395:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An examination of Dr. Sherlock's book entituled, The case of the allegiance due to sovereign powers, stated and resolved, &amp;c. by James Parkinson ...</title>
                  <author>Parkinson, James, 1653-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for David Hay,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707. --  Case of the allegiance due to soveraign powers.</term>
               <term>Allegiance --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96693:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXAMINATION OF <hi>Dr. Sherlock's Book,</hi> ENTITULED, The CASE of the ALLEGIANCE DUE TO SOVEREIGN POWERS, STATED and RESOLVED, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY <hi>JAMES PARKINSON,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>David Hay,</hi> M.DC.XCI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96693:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96693:2"/>
            <head>AN EXAMINATION OF Dr. Sherlock's Book, ENTITULED, <hi>The Caſe of the ALLEGIANCE,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>I Have Examined Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Book, Entituled, <hi>The Caſe of the Allegiance due to Sovereign Powers,</hi> &amp;c. And I muſt own, that he has done what I expected he would; For I expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted he would ſtart ſome new Doctrines to maintain his old Principles: And he has fully anſwer'd my Expectation.</p>
            <p>He tells us, <hi>he has renounc'd no Principle that ever he taught,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caſe of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance. <hi>Pref.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>excepting one in the Caſe of Reſiſtance:</hi> ſo that though he be a fallible Creature, yet, it ſeems, he is but one degree beneath Infallibility.</p>
            <p>But tho <hi>he may be miſtaken, yet this be is ſune of,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caſe of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance. <hi>Pref.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That he never acted with more ſincerity in any Affair of his whole life, than he has done in this matter, from the beginning to the end;</hi> for which I will take his word, for I had rather believe, than cenſure and judge him.</p>
            <p>Though he <hi>refus'd to take the Oaths, yet he never engag'd in any Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction againſt it, nor made it his buſineſs to diſſuade men from it.</hi> But did he not, <hi>when his Opinion was ask'd, declare his own Thoughts?</hi> And were not his Thoughts againſt it? And was not this enough for the Oracle of the Party, whenever he was conſulted, freely to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96693:3"/>declare his Thoughts? Oracles are ſometimes dumb, and will give no Anſwer; but this Doctor was always a Speaking Oracle to the Party. And who can think that he ever ſpake in vain? Who can believe, that thoſe words which dropp'd from his mouth, and dropp'd into the Ears of thoſe that admired him, and blindly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in him, could ever fail of making or confirming Non-Swearers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He had no averſion, to the Government of King</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary; and why ſhould he? The Government ſurely is almoſt as good, as it was when the Seven Right Reverend Biſhops were ſent to the <hi>Tower;</hi> it is almoſt as good, as it was when Father
<hi>Peire</hi> was at the Helm; nay, I will be bold to ſay, it is very nigh as good, as it was when he aſſiſted at the degrading of the Excellent Mr. <hi>Johnſon.</hi> But was he not thankful to God for it? no; only <hi>he had no averſton to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He prayed for King</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary. One would think, that had he prayed heartily for them in the Church, he would have own'd them in a Court of Juſtice, by taking the Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to them: No, this he could not do; he ſtill <hi>refuſed the Oaths out of pure Principles of Conſcience:</hi> but however he prayed for them. <hi>And this was a diſpoſition of mind prepared to receive ſatisfaction whenever it was offered.</hi> This I believe, and I doubt <hi>his deſire of ſatisfaction has ſecretly and inſenſibly diſtorted his Judgment:</hi> I am ſure diſtorted it is. But is his Judgment always diſtorted? Was it diſtorted while he refuſed the Oaths? And is it diſtorted now he has taken them? Yes, ſo it is; his Judgment ſtood awry before, becauſe he was not for King
<hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary:</hi> and his Judgment ſtill ſtands awry, becauſe though he ſwears Allegiance to them, yet he does it in a wrong ſenſe; he ſwears to them no otherwiſe, than he would be ready to ſwear to any Uſurper, when ſetled in the Throne. And I know not what elſe ſhould have thus <hi>diſtorted his Judgment,</hi> unleſs it were <hi>a great deſire of ſatisfaction;</hi> For the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, on which he grounds his new Allegiance, are falſe and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carious, and will ſatisfy no man, who has not as great a deſire of ſatisfaction, as he himſelf had.</p>
            <p>But though he deſired ſatisfaction, yet, it ſeems, it did not come preſently to him: he did in his thoughts ever and anon make a ſtep towards King <hi>William,</hi> but ſtill his old Principles drew him back; and in this ſtate of wavering and doubting he continued al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt two years; moving forwards, and backwards; looking ſometimes on King <hi>William,</hi> who had God's Authority to beſtow
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96693:3"/>the Preferments; and ſometimes on King <hi>James,</hi> who had (as he would make us believe) the Legal Right. <hi>He likewiſe drew up his thoughts in writing, and ſhewed them to ſome of his Friends, and told them where he ſtuck; but ſtick he did, and could find no help for it.</hi> What? was the deſire of ſatisfaction grown languid and weak? no; but though that was as ſtrong as ever, yet that alone could not do the job. Still <hi>he ſtuck, and had ſtuck to this day, had he not been relieved by Biſhop</hi> Overall<hi>'s Convocation Book.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doubtleſs the Members of that Convocation ſpent their time to good purpoſe; and Dr
<hi>Ouerall</hi> did great ſervice to the Church by regiſtring what paſſed in that venerable Aſſembly:<note place="margin">Dr <hi>Overall</hi> was no Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, nor for ſome years after that.</note> for had it not been for his Convocation-Book, this Reverend Doctor had <hi>forfeited the exerciſe of his Miniſtry for a mere miſtake.</hi> But what were the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that this Convocation-Book has wrought on him? why, it <hi>confirm'd his former Notions, and ſuggeſted ſome new thoughts to him, which removed thoſe difficulties that he could not conquer before.</hi> So that, it ſeems, he would not have us think, he had all his good No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from the Convocation-Book; no, he had many of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he read it, and that Book did only confirm them. And beſides all this, he tells us, That
<hi>The venerable Authority of a Convocation gave him greater freedom and liberty of thinking,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Preface.</note> 
               <hi>which the apprehenſion of novelty and ſingularity had cramp'd before.</hi> And now the Doctor ſwells, and is puffed up with the Sacred. Authority of a Convocation. His Soul was not at liberty before; it was chain'd and fetter'd, and he was afraid to let his thoughts rove and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; but, now he has the Convocation on his ſide, his thoughts are at liberty, and he reſolves to wander; and I likewiſe reſolve to follow him, as far as I ſhall ſee it neceſſary.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 1. Caſe of Allegianc.</note>At his firſt ſetting out, he complains that the <hi>Controverſy is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plext;</hi> but I doubt, that before I ſhall get to the end of his Book, I ſhall have greater reaſon to complain, that he has perplext it more. But what is it that has perplexed the Controverſie? Why, it is <hi>the intermixing the diſpute of Right, with the duty of Obedience:</hi> as if we could be bound to obey one who has no right to our Obedience:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 1.</note> it is a <hi>making the legal Right of Princes to their Thrones,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>the only reaſon and foundation of the Allegiance of Subjects:</hi> and I would fain know what other foundation of Allegiance there can be?<note place="margin">Biſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi>'s Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoral Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>p.</hi> 6.</note> For <hi>Allegiance is Obedience according to Law; that is to ſay, not a blind and abſolute Obedience, but ſuch an Obedience as is defined and limited by the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96693:4"/>
            <p>He blames thoſe that have not taken the Oaths,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 2.</note> becauſe <hi>they go wholly upon this Principle, That Allegiance is due only to Legal Right: and take away,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that, and you remove all the difficulties they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour under;</hi> and I ſuppoſe it is for their ſakes, that he has, as far as in him lay, taken away the Legal Right from their Majeſties, that ſo he might remove all the difficulties which the Non-ſwearers labour under. But he ſeems not to care what becomes of their Majeſties, nor what difficulties he throws them into. And he blames likewiſe many of <hi>thoſe that have writ in defence of the new Oaths,</hi> becauſe <hi>they ſuppoſe that a Legal Right is neceſſary to make Allegiance due,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>and have therefore endeavoured to juſtify the Legal Right of their preſent Majeſties.</hi> This it ſeems is become a Crime, <hi>to juſtify the Legal Right of Their preſent Majeſties,</hi> which yet if we do not juſtify, we condemn our ſelves. But why ſhould we not juſtify the Legal Right of Their preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties? Why ſhould we, for the ſake of a few Non-ſwearees, betray our Cauſe, and tacitly own, that we believe King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> to be Uſurpers? He gives two reaſons for this; and I think he is a very bold Man that will venture to give reaſons for ſo unreaſonable a thing. Now his Reaſons are, 1ſt, Becauſe <hi>it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to diſpute the Rights of Princes.</hi> 2d, Becauſe <hi>it is unneceſſary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Becauſe 'tis unfit to diſpute the Rights of Princes:</hi> But though it may not be fit to diſpute the Right of a Prince,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 1.</note> when ſettled on the Throne, yet it might have been fit to aſſert it; though <hi>no Government can permit it to be a Queſtion,</hi> yet it might have been his declared Opinion; one would think that he, out of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to his Royal Patron, ſhould have own'd him to be Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King; nay, methinks his intereſt ſhould have prompted him to it: For I muſt tell him, there is this in the caſe, which he little thought of, That if K. <hi>William</hi> have not a legal Right to the Crown, Dr.
<hi>W. Sherlock</hi> can have no legal Right to the Maſterſhip of the Temple: For 'tis the Law alone, that inveſts King <hi>William</hi> with a Power to beſtow theſe Preferments; and therefore if the King be only King <hi>de facto,</hi> that is, in his ſenſe, an Uſurper, I know not how the Doctor will be able to make out, that he is any more than <hi>de facto</hi> Maſter of the Temple, without a Legal Right to his Place. A froward Prince would hardly bear ſuch ill treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as this, I'm ſure his Legal King would not; and a mild King does not deſerve it from him. I doubt not but he has done a great deal of miſchief (though I do not ſay he deſign'd it) by refuſing to take the Oaths; And did it become him to publiſh
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96693:4"/>ſuch a Book to the World, and, by implication, declare to all his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Subjects, That he for his part does not look upon King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> to whom he has ſworn Allegiance, to be any more than a King and Queen <hi>de facto,</hi> that is (according to him) Uſurpers?</p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſays, <hi>'Tis unneceſſary to defend the Legal Right of King</hi> William
<hi>and Queen</hi> Mary: For whom is it unneceſſary? For him, it may be, becauſe he does not believe it; but 'tis not unneceſſary for thoſe that own their Legal Right: Nay, there is nothing more neceſſary than this; and therefore two Parliaments, this and the laſt, have recogniz'd their Title. But it ſeems thoſe Parliaments did a very needleſs thing, and wanted this Doctor to give them better Advice; for he that can ſit in his Study, and there make and unmake Kings at his pleaſure, may ſurely be fit to give Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel to Parliaments.</p>
            <p>The Doctor and I are in one thing agreed, That Allegiance is due to King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> but we differ about the foundation and reaſon of our Allegiance: He thinks
<hi>that we ought not to take the conſideration of Right into the Settlement of Government;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 18.</note> for he ſays, <hi>A Prince may be ſettled in his Throne without Legal Right, and when he is ſo, God has made him our King, and requires our Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:</hi> and I cannot be of his Opinion. He ſays, <hi>That his Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance may be due to one who has no Legal Right to Govern him;</hi> I ſay, that I owe Allegiance to none but him who has the Legal Right.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore do theſe two things:
<list>
                  <item>1. I ſhall give my own Opinion, with the Grounds and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of it.</item>
                  <item>2. I ſhall examine his.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="subsection">
               <head>I. I ſhall give my Opinion, with the Grounds and Reaſons of it; which I ſhall do in theſe following Propoſitions:</head>
               <p n="1">1. Allegiance, is Obedience according to Law.</p>
               <p n="2">2. No Man can have any Right to my Allegiance, who is not my Lawful King. Theſe Propoſitions are, I think, in themſelves evident, and need no proof: And therefore.</p>
               <p n="3">3. King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> are Lawful and Rightful King and Queen of
<hi>England,</hi> and the Dominions thereunto belonging: This appears plainly from that Declaration which the Lords and Commons Aſſembled at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> preſented to their Highneſſes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96693:5"/>the Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange, Feb.</hi> 13. 1688. wherein they ſet forth,<note place="margin">Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Lords and Commons preſented to the Prince and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range.</hi>
                  </note> That <hi>King</hi> James, <hi>by the aſſiſtance of divers evil Counſellors, Judges, and Miniſters, employ'd by him, had endeavoured to extirpate the Proteſtant Religion, and the Laws and Liberties of this Kingdom,</hi> and many inſtances they give of his miſgovernment; and that he had <hi>Abdicated the Government, and the Throne was become Vacant.</hi> And then they aſſert the ſeveral Rights of the Subject, which the late King had notoriouſly violated; and laſt of all, <hi>Having an entire con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence that his Highneſs the Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>would preſerve them from the violation of their Rights, and from all attempts upon their Religion, Laws and Liberties; they reſolve, That</hi> William
<hi>and</hi> Mary, <hi>Prince and Princeſs of</hi> Orange, <hi>be, and be declared King and Queen of</hi> England, France <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and the Dominions thereunto belonging.</hi> And
<hi>the Prince and Princeſs of</hi> Orange, <hi>at the Requeſt, and by the Advice of the Lords and Commons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Williel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> &amp; <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae. c.</hi> 1.</note>
                  <hi>did accept the Crown and Royal Dignity of King and Queen of</hi> England, France <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and the Dominions and Territories thereto belonging.</hi> They did <hi>accept</hi> the Crown, they did not <hi>ſnatch</hi> it by force and violence; They were no Conquerors, no Uſurpers.</p>
               <p>And afterwards, in an Act paſt <hi>December</hi> 16. 1689. the ſame Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament recogniz'd their Title in theſe words; <hi>The Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, ſeriouſly conſidering how it hath pleas'd Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God in his marvellous Providence, and merciful Goodneſs to this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to provide and preſerve Their ſaid Majeſties Royal Perſons moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily to reign over us upon the Throne of Their Anceſtors (for which they render unto him from the bottom of their hearts their humbleſt thanks and praiſes) do truly, firmly, aſſuredly, and in the ſincerity of their hearts, think, and do hereby recognize, acknowledge and declare, That King</hi> James <hi>the Second having abdicated the Government, and Their Majeſties having accepted the Crown and Royal Dignity, Their ſaid Majeſties did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, were, and are, and of right ought to be by the Laws of this Realm, our Sovereign. Liege Lord and Lady, King and Queen of</hi> England, France <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and the Dominions thereunto belonging; in, and to whoſe Princely Perſons the Royal State, Crown and Dignity of the ſaid Realms, with all Honours, Titles,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to the ſame belonging and apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, are moſt fully, rightfully and intirely inveſted and incorporated, united and annexed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when that Parliament was diſſolved, and a new one ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to meet at
<hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> there was a new Recognition of Their Title in theſe words, <hi>We Your Majeſties moſt Humble and Loyal Subjects, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96693:5"/>Parliament Aſſembled, do beſeech Your Moſt Excellent Majeſties, that it may be publiſh'd and declar'd in this High Court of Parliament, and Enacted by Authority of the ſame, That we do recognize, and acknowledg Your Majeſties were, are, and of Right ought to be by the Laws of this Realm, our Sovereign Liege Lord and Lady, King and Queen of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if this be not a Legal Title, I know not what a Legal Title means. It is as good a Title as
<hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor had; as good a one, as <hi>W.</hi> 1. <hi>W.</hi> 2. <hi>Hen</hi>
1. K. <hi>Stephen, Hen.</hi> 2. K. <hi>John, Hen.</hi> 3. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4, 5, 6,
7. Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> or Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> (one or other of thoſe two Queens) either had, or could pretend to; and theſe, whom I have mentioned, had as truly a Legal Right to the Crown, as any of the reſt whom I make no mention of: And the true Reaſon why I inſtance in theſe, is this, Becauſe it is certain that none of theſe were Kings by any Divine Right of Succeſſion.</p>
               <p>If Proximity of Blood be abſolutely neceſſary to a Legal Title, then <hi>Edw.</hi> the Confeſſor had none; for when he aſcended the Throne, <hi>Edgar Atheling,</hi> his Elder Brother's Son, was alive. Then <hi>W.</hi> 1. had none, both becauſe he was illegitimate, and alſo becauſe <hi>Edgar Atheling</hi> was ſtill living. Then <hi>W.</hi> 2. and <hi>Hen.</hi>
1. could have none, while their Elder Brother <hi>Robert</hi> was living. Then K. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> could have none; for the Right of Blood was in <hi>Maud</hi> the Empreſs, <hi>Hen.</hi> the firſt's Daughter. Then <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. could have none, ſo long as his Mother <hi>Maud</hi> was alive. Then K. <hi>John</hi> could have none; for <hi>Arthur,</hi> his Elder Brother's Son, had all the Right that Proximity of Blood could give. Then <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. could have none, at leaſt, not before the 24th year of his Reign or thereabouts; at what time <hi>Eleanor,</hi> Siſter to Prince <hi>Arthur,</hi> died. Then <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. could have none, during the Life of his unfortunate Father <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. who was Depos'd. Then <hi>Hen.</hi> 4, 5, 6, 7. could have none, there being another Family which had the proximity of Blood on their ſide. Then Q.
<hi>Mary,</hi> or Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> (one or other of them) could have none; for it is certain that one of the two muſt be illegitimate, becauſe <hi>Katherine,</hi> Q. <hi>Mary</hi>'s Mother, was living at the time when Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was born: And yet we do not find that any Learned and Pious Biſhops, or any other dignified Clergy-men, ever refuſed to accept of Eccleſiaſtical Preferments from any of the foremention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Princes, and to ſwear Allegiance to them. Nor can it be ſaid, that they ſwore Allegiance to them as to Kings <hi>de facto,</hi> but not <hi>de jure;</hi> at leaſt wiſe, this cannot be affirmed of thoſe who lived be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Reign of <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. for then aroſe this diſtinction, and not before.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96693:6"/>
               <p>The <hi>Scotch</hi> Parliament calls this a Villanous diſtinction: I think I may ſay, it is a diſtinction that is not well grounded; for it ſeems to me to be founded on a falſe Principle, <hi>That Proximity of Blood gives ſuch an indefeaſible Right or Title to the Crown, that he, who is next on the Royal Line, whatever his natural or moral incapacities are, cannot be barr'd from ſucceding to the Throne:</hi> Which is directly contrary to a Statute made in the
13th of Q. <hi>Eliz. ch.</hi> 1. wherein it is affirmed, That <hi>the King, Lords, and Commons, have right to limit and bind the Crown of this Realm, and the Deſcent, Inheritance, and Government thereof:</hi> And 'twas by the ſaid Statute made Treaſon, during the Life of that Queen, to hold, affirm, or maintain the contrary; and, after her deceaſe, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of Goods and Chattels; and I know not of any Law of God that the Queen and Parliament broke when they made that Statute. A King <hi>de facto</hi> is not, as the Doctor imagines, an Uſurper, but he is a Lawful King; He is one to whom our Allegiance is due, (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from a Statute made in the 11th of <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>ch.</hi> 1.) and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is due to none, but him who has a Legal Right; for Allegiance is <hi>Obedience according to Law,</hi> and conſequently muſt be paid to him to whom the Law directs us to pay it; and to ſay that the Law di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects us to pay our Obedience to one, who has no Legal Right to it, does not ſound well.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It follows from hence, that our Allegiance is due to K. <hi>VVilliam</hi> and Q.
<hi>Mary;</hi> for it is due to a Lawful King, and it has been ſhew'd, That Their Majeſties are Lawful and Rightful King and Queen. And this is the foundation of my Allegiance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="subsection">
               <head>II. I muſt now examin. Dr. <hi>Sherlook</hi>'s Opinion concerning this matter.</head>
               <p>His notion is this,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Page</hi> 10.</note> 
                  <hi>That all Sovereign Princes, who are ſettled in their Thrones, are plac'd there by God, and inveſted with his Authority, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt be obeyed by all Subjects as the Miniſters of God, without enquiring into their Legal Right and Title to the Throne.</hi> And he tells us, That <hi>the Convocation has determin'd two great points, whereon this whole Controverſy turns:</hi> 1. <hi>That thoſe Princes, who have no Legal Right to their Thrones, may yet have God's Authority.</hi> 2. <hi>That when they are throughly ſettled in their Thrones, they are inveſted with God's Authority, and muſt be reverenc'd and obeyed by all, who live within their Territories and Dominions, as well Prieſts as People.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is his Doctrine, <hi>And this,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I will endeavour to prove from the Authority of Scripture and Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96693:6"/>
               <p>Scripture and Reaſon I am always ready to hear; he that brings me a plain Scripture proof, commands my aſſent; and he that gives me a good Reaſon, will eaſily perſuade me: And therefore though the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Authority of a Convocation ſtands in the front of his Book, yet I intend it ſhall Lackey after his Reaſons, and his Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Proofs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT I.</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Proofs from Scripture and Reaſon Examined.</head>
               <p>HIS <hi>Proofs from Reaſon and Scripture muſt,</hi> he ſays, <hi>neceſſarily be intermixt, and interwoven with each other; and to ſet the matter in as clear a light as he can, he reduceth the whole into the Propoſitions following:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prop. 1. <hi>That all Civil Power and Authority is from God,</hi> &amp;c. This is looſly expreſſed, and in general terms, and may be allow'd to be in ſome ſenſe true, and therefore I will let it paſs, and will deſire him to conſider, that ſo is every thing from God, except Sin; ſo are Riches and Honours from God, tho Men beſtow them; ſo is the Doctor himſelf from God, tho his Father begat him; and ſo is his Book from God; for God gave him Power to write it, though I do not think, God gave him any Authority.</p>
               <p>Prop. 2. <hi>Civil Power and Authority is no otherwiſe from God, than as God gives this Power and Authority to particular perſons,</hi> &amp;c. A great diſcovery this! That God does in ſome ſenſe give whatever may be ſaid in any ſenſe to come from him; as if a creature could ſnatch any thing from his Creator againſt his will. But how is Civil Power and Authority from God? And how does he give Civil Power and Authority to particular perſons? He tells us,</p>
               <p>Prop. 3. <hi>There are but three ways whereby God gives this Power and Authority to any perſons;</hi> either</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>By Nature; Thus Parents have a natural ſuperiority over their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; but by what bounds this Paternal and Patriarchal Authority was li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, we cannot tell; 'tis in vain to enquire after it now:</hi> And ſo he has taken his leave of Sir <hi>Robert Filmer</hi>'s
<hi>Patriarcha.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>By a particular nomination; Thus God made Kings only in Jewry;</hi> but this does not at all concern us.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96693:7"/>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>By the diſpoſals of his Providence:</hi> That God Governs the World, I am very ſure, for his Word aſſures me of it; and 'tis the greateſt comfort of my Life, to conſider that there is a Wiſe, Juſt and Good God who Rules the World. But how does he Rule the World? How does he ſet up and pull down Kings, and bring about the great Revolutions and Changes of Governments? Does God preſcribe to any people a form of Government? Does he appoint or dictate the particular Laws of each Country? Does he nominate the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magiſtrate? Does he ſet bounds to the Supreme Governor's Power? No, he does none of theſe things; but leaves them to the Reaſon and Prudence of Men. But yet God is not altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concern'd; he does not ſit on his Throne in Heaven a mere Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of human Affairs, without ever intermedling in them: But he interpoſes, as becomes a Wiſe Governor of the World, by directing and guiding the minds; by moving and inclining, by checking and reſtraining the wills of his creatures in an unknown manner. How, or in what manner he directs the greater and the leſſer Wheels of Providence, we cannot tell; but that he does direct them, is not to be doubted.</p>
               <p>In the general, I think we ought to lay down this Rule, Never to aſcribe to God any thing that is unworthy of him, that is diſagreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his Wiſdom, or Juſhice, or Equity, or Goodneſs; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſince his Divine Laws are full of Wiſdom, Equity, Juſtice, and Goodneſs, we ought never to think that he who has oblig'd Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind by ſuch excellent Laws, does by any ſecret influence move them to a violation of them. He indeed ſees the unruly Wills and Affections of Men, and knows that they will abuſe the Power they have, and unjuſtly catch at more to oppreſs their Brethren; and he in his Wiſdom permits ſometimes that they ſhould attain their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ends; but when ever he does ſo, we muſt not take it for a mark of his approbation; nor argue thus, That becauſe they proſper, therefore God is pleaſed with their doings; for he will certainly, ſooner or later, puniſh them for what they do. But you'll ſay, when an Uſurper proſpers, and aſcends the Throne, and is ſetled in it, Does not God then make him a King, and inveſt him with his Authority? No ſuch matter; he is ſtill a private Man, without Right to Kingly Government, unleſs an Unjuſt action can create a Right. But though an unjuſt action cannot create a Right, yet God can give him a Right. True; But how ſhall I know that he does ſo? That, ſays the Doctor, you may know by the event; if you ſee him able to cruſh whom he pleaſes, and ſeated upon the Royal Throne,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96693:7"/>aſſure your ſelf, that God has ſet him up, and made him a King; for
<hi>the moſt high ruleth in the Kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomſoever he will, and ſetteth up over it the baſeſt of Men.</hi> Now in anſwer to this,<note place="margin">Dan.
4.17</note> I allow the Doctor, that God does in ſome ſenſe ſet up a Tyrant; but then I deſire him to conſider, that Satan likewiſe ſets him up, and wicked Men ſet him up, and he ſets up himſelf. He ſets up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by abuſing the Power he has, by encreaſing it more and more through his reſtleſs Ambition, and by raiſing of Forces to gain the Sovereign Power. And wicked Men ſet him up, by giving him aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance for the accompliſhing of his wicked deſigns; not that they love to be Slaves, but they are willing to enſlave others, and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize over them. And Satan ſets him up, by tempting him to get the Sovereign Power, and make himſelf a God upon Earth. And laſtly, God ſets him up; But how does God ſet him up? Why, God gives him thoſe natural powers and faculties both of Mind and Body, which fit him for great Undertakings; and moreover he in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence gives him many favourable opportunities for encreaſing his Wealth, and enlarging his Power, and ſtrengthning his Intereſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his Fellow Subjects: And theſe are a Ladder, by which he may poſſibly climb to the Sovereignty. And though God has in his Word forbidden him to invade the Rights of others, and advance himſelf to the Throne by unjuſt means, yet he permits him to do ſo; though he, who ſets bounds to the raging Sea, <hi>And ſays, Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſhalt thou come, but no further;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job
38 11.</note> 
                  <hi>and here ſhall thy proud waves be ſtay'd;</hi> could eaſily reſtrain an Ambitious Uſurper, and ſtop him from aſcending the Royal Throne; yet he, for wiſe ends, ſuffers him to go on and proſper in his unjuſt Enterprizes. Thus God ſets up a Tyrant, (but gives him no Authority) and the Devil ſets him up, and wicked Men ſet him up, and he ſets up himſelf. And this is agreeable to the Style and Language of Scripture, which tells us in one place, That <hi>Satan ſtood up againſt</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and provoked</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid <hi>to number</hi> Iſrael;<note place="margin">1 Chron. 21.1. 2 Sam. 24.1.</note> And in another place,
<hi>That the anger of the Lord was kindled againſt</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and he moved</hi> David
<hi>againſt them, to ſay, Go number</hi> Iſrael <hi>and</hi> Judah: So that here the ſame ſinful Action is in words aſcrib'd to God and Satan, for both are here ſaid to have mov'd
<hi>David</hi> to number <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the word in the Original is in both places the ſame; it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſignifies to Seduce, Entice, or Perſuade; and who will think that God does perſuade or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice men to ſin, otherwiſe than by giving Satan permiſſion and leave to tempt and entice them?</p>
               <p>Well then, God never ſets up Uſurpers ſo as to give them any
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96693:8"/>Authority;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 13.</note> and therefore that is very falſe which Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers for a certain truth, <hi>viz. That God never ſuffers an Aſpiring Prince to aſcend the Throne, but when he thinks fit to make him King;</hi> for he is not made a King upon his aſcending the Throne, nor has he any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Authority, unleſs the Dr. can prove, that barely to aſcend the Throne, is to be a King: And when he can prove that, I'll under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to make out, That to aſcend the Temple-Pulpit, is to be Maſter of the Temple; and then he muſt have a care of getting another to preach for him.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 13.</note> 
                  <hi>But,</hi> ſays he, <hi>unleſs all Kings are ſet up by God, and inveſted with his Authority, we can never know what Kings have God's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, who thoſe are whom we mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t obey out of Conſcience, and whom we muſt not obey</hi> Which is juſt as if one ſhould ſay, Unleſs every one that comes up into the Temple-Pulpit be Maſter of the Temple, one cannot be able to know, who is, and who is not Maſter of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. One would admire that one, who has ſo good a faculty of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining Myſteries, ſhould not be able to diſtinguiſh between a King and a Tyrant, nor know the difference between Accepting, and Snatching of a Crown.</p>
               <p>Prop. 4. <hi>All Kings are equally rightful with reſpect to God.</hi> This I utterly deny. For God ſurely ſees and knows, that one aſcends the Throne by Fraud, and Perjury, and Violence, and Oppreſſion, and Murther; and that another is freely choſen by the Voice of the People, for the great eſteem they have of his Juſtice, and Valour, and other noble Qualities that fit him for the exerciſe of Sovereign Power. Now will any man ſay, that a Holy and Juſt God makes no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction between theſe two? Will any man affirm, that God puts no difference between one that enters by the Door into the Sheepfold, and another that climbs up ſome other way? Between the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd who feeds the Sheep, and a Thief or Robber that comes to ſteal them? Men do not judge them to be equally Rightful Kings, and yet Men judge by a Rule that God has given them,
<hi>viz.</hi> the Rule of right Reaſon; and why ſhould we think that God judges otherwiſe in this Caſe, than Men do? Men, who judge thus, are not miſtaken in their Judgments; and I do not ſee any reaſon, why God, who cannot be miſtaken, ſhould not judge in this Caſe as Men, who are not miſtaken, do. In ſhort, If Men, who think an Uſurper is not a Rightful King, be not miſtaken, it is reaſonable to conclude, God thinks ſo too; and on the other hand, If God thinks an Uſurper to be as much a Rightful King as any other, methinks this ſhould be a very good Reaſon for us to think ſo too: For if we think as God thinks, we ſhall not err in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96693:8"/>our thoughts. But how does he prove that all Kings are equally rightful with reſpect to God? <hi>Becauſe,</hi> ſays he, <hi>they are plac'd in the Throne by God.</hi> And are they not plac'd in the Throne by Men? is not the hand of Man viſible in this matter? Nay, is not the hand of Man the only viſible hand? and do not the hands of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Men ſet the Crown on the Head of an Uſurper? and does he think, that ſuch a one is with reſpect to God as Rightful a King, as God's Anointed King <hi>David</hi> was? I grant, that if God were the only Perſon that plac'd Princes in the Throne; if he did always himſelf put the Scepter into their hands, and by a Voice from Heaven, or an expreſs nomination, made Kings; there would then be no queſtion, but all would be equally Rightful Kings, though not equally good ones: As
<hi>Saul</hi>'s Title was as good as that of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> though he was not ſo good a King. But ſince Men are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in advancing Princes to the Throne, and they may, and do often, by unjuſt means place them thereon; to ſay that all Kings are equally Rightful with reſpect to God, is to ſay that God has no regard to the ſinful Means that are us'd to ſet up ſuch Kings; it is to confound the Notions of Good and Evil, of Right and Wrong, and to turn the World into a mere <hi>Bedlam.</hi> Add to this, That if all Kings were equally Rightful with reſpect to God, then why ſhould he complain as he did, <hi>They have ſet up Kings, but not by me;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 8.4.</note> 
                  <hi>they have made Princes, and I knew it not?</hi> Since, if what this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor affirms, be true, God himſelf ſet up the Kings which they ſet up, and made the Princes which they made; and did as truly make them, <hi>As if they had been expreſly nominated, and anointed by a Prophet at God's Command, as</hi> Saul <hi>and</hi> David
<hi>were.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude this Head, If all Princes when they are advanced to the Throne, by what means ſoever they are lifted up above their Brethren, be equally Rightful Kings, then ſurely they have equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Commiſſion from God, to act as Kings; but Uſurpers have no Commiſſion at all from God to rule his people; they have no Authority, and they can have none, unleſs God's word has loſt its Authority; for I'm ſure, that forbids all unjuſt Uſurpations, and thereby plainly tells us, That Uſurpers have no Authority, unleſs God ſhould give them Authority to do what he in his Word has forbidden; which I hope the Doctor will not affirm.</p>
               <p>Prop. 5. <hi>The diſtinction then between a King</hi> de Jure, <hi>and a King</hi> de Facto,
<hi>relates only to Humane Laws,</hi> &amp;c. If by a King <hi>de Facto;</hi> he means, as it is plain he does, an Uſurper; and by a King <hi>de Jure,</hi> a Rightul King; I grant, that if the foregoing Propoſition were
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96693:9"/>true, this would be true too; for if all Kings be equally Rightfu with reſpect to God, then all Kings are Kings <hi>de Jure</hi> with reſpect to God; and conſequently, as he ſays, the diſtinction of a King <hi>de Jure</hi> and <hi>de Facto</hi> would relate only to Humane Laws: So that here is nothing elſe aſſerted in this Propoſition, but what was in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Only I muſt tell him what I have obſerv'd already; That this diſtinction is not to be allowed with reſpect to Humane Laws; for in <hi>England,</hi> whoever is a King <hi>de Facto,</hi> is alſo a King <hi>de Jure,</hi> for he has a right to our Allegiance.</p>
               <p>Prop. 6. <hi>We can have but one King at a time;</hi> I'll give him this, and I hope King
<hi>William</hi> is the Doctor's King.</p>
               <p>Prop. 7. <hi>He is our King, who is ſetled in the Throne in the actual Adminiſtration of Sovereign Power,</hi> &amp;c. If he means by <hi>ſetled,</hi> legally ſetled, I agree with him; otherwiſe I deny it. For I know of no other Settlement, but a Legal one, that can make a King: A Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without Law, which the Doctor ſpeaks of, is the Settlement not of a King, but of a powerful Uſurper: 'tis juſt ſuch a Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as a Thief may have for a time, who breaks open another Man's Houſe, and turns him out, and takes poſſeſſion of it.</p>
               <p>Prop. 8. <hi>Allegiance is due only to the King.</hi> This I freely give him. And from hence he concludes, That <hi>we muſt pay our Allegiance to him who is our King, though without a Legal Right.</hi> His Suppoſition is falſe; for he ſuppoſes, that one may be his King without a Legal Right, which I deny: He may be, and is an Uſurper, who has no Legal Right, but he is not our King: he is a private Man, intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding himſelf into a publick Office, which he is not call'd to: and no Allegiance is due to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But,</hi> ſays he, <hi>our Allegiance is due to him who is our King, though without a Legal Right, becauſe Allegiance is due only to God's Authority, not to a bare Legal Title without God's Authority.</hi> Here he ſeparates two things, which do always go together; a Legal Right, and God's Authority; for God does not give Authority to any, but thoſe who have a Legal Right. I grant, that God may nominate Kings if he pleaſes, and then doubtleſs they would have his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority without a Legal Right; nor would they need any Legal Right, ſince they would have a Divine Right, which would be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But ſince he does not nominate any Kings, as he formerly did in <hi>Jewry,</hi> we have no way to know who has God's Authority, but by knowing who has the Legal Right.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:96693:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. II.</hi> An Examination of ſome other Reaſons and Arguments, urg'd by Dr.
<hi>Sherlock</hi> for the further Confirmation of his Doctrine, contain'd in his 4th Section.</head>
               <p n="1">1. HE obſerves, <hi>That the Scripture has given us no Directions in this Caſe, but to ſubmit and pay all the Allegiance of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to the preſent Powers.</hi> Nor was it neceſſary that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhould give us any other directions in this caſe; for why may not Reaſon without Scripture direct us in this caſe, as it did di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Men before the Epiſtle of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans</hi> was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten? But <hi>Scripture,</hi> he ſays,
<hi>makes no diſtinction, that ever he could find, between rightful Kings and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers.</hi> And what then? Scripture makes no diſtinction that I can find, between my right Hand and my Left; but a little Senſe and Reaſon will teach me to diſtinguiſh. Was it neceſſary for the Apoſtle, when he taught, <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher Powers,</hi> to have added, <hi>if they be truly the higher Powers; but if they be not the higher Powers, you need not be ſubject to them?</hi> Was it needful, when he ſaid, <hi>Servants obey your Maſters,</hi> to have immediately ſubjoin'd this, <hi>if they be really your Maſters; but if they be not your Maſters, you need not obey them?</hi> Was it neceſſary, when he gave this general Command,
<hi>Wives ſubmit your ſelves to your own Husbands,</hi> to have immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately added, <hi>if they be indeed your own Husbands; but if they be not your Husbands, you need not ſubmit your ſelves to them?</hi> No more was it neceſſary for the Apoſtle to diſtinguiſh between a rightful King and an Uſurper; becauſe every one that has but common Senſe and Reaſon, can do this with eaſe, without Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical help. An Uſurper of Royal Power, is not to be reckon'd amongſt St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s higher Powers; nor is he any more my King, as being not called to that Office, than he can be called my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, with whom I have made no Contract: And therefore to ſay, <hi>the Apoſtle here ſpeaks only of lawful Powers</hi> is not (as he ſays)
<hi>gratis dictum;</hi> it being the only reaſonable interpretation that the words can bear.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Had there</hi> (ſays he) <hi>been any ſuch Rule before given, to ſubmit to lawful Powers, but not to ſubmit to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers, there had been ſome
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96693:10"/>pretence for underſtanding St.</hi> Paul<hi>'s all Power of all legal Power; but there being nothing like this any where in Scripture, if he had intended any ſuch diſtinction, he ought to have ſaid it in expreſs words, or elſe no Body could reaſonably have underſtood him, to intend this Precept of Subjection to the higher Powers, only of Powers that had a legal Right.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, on the contrary, ſay I, if St. <hi>Paul</hi> had not intended any ſuch diſtinction, he ſhould in expreſs words have forbidden ſuch a diſtinction; he ſhould have told us that we ought not to diſtinguiſh between rightful Kings and Uſurpers; for that we ſhould thus diſtinguiſh, Reaſon will teach us; but that we ſhould not diſtinguiſh, can be only Matter of Faith. I would think my Obedience due to an Uſurper, if I had plain Scripture for it; but Reaſon, I am ſure, does not teach it. The Doctor him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf formerly taught, that when St.
<hi>Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>All Power is of God, he means only legal Power:</hi> and that I believe was a true Expoſition of the Text: But it ſeems he has now renounced it, as he tells us in his Preface to the <hi>Caſe of Allegiance,</hi> &amp;c. and I know no other reaſon he has for ſo doing, but only this, becauſe it cannot ſtand with his new Doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Criticiſm,</hi> he ſays, <hi>between</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>and</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>will not do:</hi> No matter for that, I lay no weight upon it; and yet by the by, I muſt tell him, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> do differ in proper ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; for the former is Power, whether legal or no; the latter is only legal Power, or Authority.</p>
               <p>What he ſays, <hi>That if St.</hi> Paul <hi>had meant only legal Powers, then in order to the fulfilling of this Precept, it would be neceſſary for Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to examine the Titles of Princes, and to that end to be well skill'd in the Hiſtory and Laws of a Nation,</hi> &amp;c. is ſo weak an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, that it neither needs, nor deſerves an Anſwer: For though he will not take the Judgment of two Parliaments, that have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared King <hi>William</hi> and Queen
<hi>Mary</hi> to be lawful King and Queen of <hi>England;</hi> yet others think it reaſonable to reſt ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with their Declaration.</p>
               <p>What he adds concerning the Titles of the Roman Emperors in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Time,<note place="margin">Enquiry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</note> 
                  <hi>That they were either ſtark naught, or doubtful,</hi> I cannot allow; <hi>for ſince both the People and Senate had acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the Power, that</hi> Auguſtus <hi>had indeed violently uſurped; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Legal, when it was thus ſubmitted to and confirmed both by Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and People; and it was eſtabliſhed in his Family by a long Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription,</hi> when this Epiſtle was written.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:96693:10"/>
               <p>But he goes on, and tells us, <hi>That the Reaſon the Apoſtle gives for ſubmiſſion to higher Powers, is not a legal Right, but the Authority of God.</hi> To which I anſwer, That the Authority of God does ſuppoſe a legal Right, God giving no Authority to any one to rule over others, who are not legally deputed to the Office.</p>
               <p>God's Authority is, I conceive, a Divine Right: Now we may diſtinguiſh of a Divine Right; for,</p>
               <p n="1">1. A Prince may have a Divine Right to aſcend the Royal Throne: Such a Divine Right as this <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David</hi> had, who were expreſly marked out by God; and ſuch a Divine Right would any Prince have, if God ſhould make any declaration in favour of him.<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets</hi> Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry into the meaſures of Obedience.
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>But this pretence of a Divine Delegation can be carried no further, than to thoſe who are thus expreſly marked out; and is unjuſtly claim'd by thoſe who can prove no ſuch Declaration to have been ever made in favour of them or their Families; nor does it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear reaſonable to conclude, from their being in poſſeſſion, that it is the Will of God that it ſhould be ſo: This juſtifies all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers when they are ſuccesful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. A Prince may have a Divine Right to ſecure him in the poſſeſſion of the Throne; ſuch a Divine Right has every Prince that has a legal Right; and indeed every private Man has ſuch a Divine Right to ſecure him in the poſſeſſion of that which is his by Law.
<hi>And though a Man has no Divine Right to his Property,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>
                  <hi>but has acquir'd it by humane Means, ſuch as Succeſſion or Induſtry; yet he has a ſecurity for the enjoyment of it from a Divine Right: So though Princes have no immediate Warrants from Heaven, either for their Original Titles, or for the extent of them, yet they are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd in the poſſeſſion of them by the Principles and Rules of natural Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Saviour's Argument,</hi> ſays he, <hi>relies wholly on the poſſeſſion of Power: Whoſe Image and Superſcription has it?</hi> In anſwer to this, I will only give him Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>'s Comment upon the place:
<q>The coining of Mony is part of the Supream Power, or Regal Prerogative, incommunicable to any other; and your acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging this to be the Currant Coin ſuppoſes Ceſar, whoſe Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nature it has, to be your lawful Prince, to whom therefore the Tribute is due, as to the legal Protector of your Civil Commerce: Look therefore upon your Coin for the ſtating your Queſtion, whoſe Image or Signature it has on it. And when they confeſs'd it to be the Roman Emperor's Image, our Saviour thence concluded, <hi>Render therefore unto Ceſar the things
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96693:11"/>that are Ceſar</hi>'s; you that acknowledg Ceſar's Supremacy over the Jews, ought not to diſpute, but pay him that Tribute which is due to him as Supream.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>This,</hi> he ſays, <hi>gives the caſieſt and moſt intelligible account of the Original of Humane Government, that all Power is from God.</hi> All Men do not think the Account he gives of Government is ſo eaſy and intelligible; but it matters not how eaſy and intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it is, if it be not true.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>This Doctrine,</hi> he ſays, <hi>is founded on the ſame Principle with the Doctrine of Non-reſistance or Paſſive-Obedience.</hi> Is it ſo? then it has a very weak Foundation, and there is good hope it will not ſtand long; for Paſſive Obedience, as taught by him, is knock'd down. And I wonder much that Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> would reprint his Book intitled the <hi>Caſe of Reſiſtance of the Supream Powers ſtated,</hi> &amp;c. without taking any notice of Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi>'s Remarks upon it. But he thinks he may well deſpiſe that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Books, tho written with Judgment; becauſe the Author himſelf, after all his Merits, is ſo little regarded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. III.</hi> Reaſons and Objections againſt Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Doctrine.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe Firſt Objection that I ſhall make, is an Objection that he himſelf rais'd againſt his own Doctrine; but I think he has not well anſwered it, and therefore it ſtill remains an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection againſt him; I will deliver it in his own Words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This makes a Prince loſe his Right by being notoriouſly injur'd; for if a proſperous <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper gets into the Throne, and ſettles himſelf there, God has taken away his Crown, and given it to another, and therefore he ought not to attempt the recovery of his Throne, (nor any other Prince to aſſiſt him in it) which is to oppoſe God, and to challenge that, which he has no longer any Right to.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the Doctor's own Objection, and I think 'tis a very ſtrong one; let us hear what he ſays to it; for I do not think he has given a ſatisfactory Anſwer.</p>
               <p>He anſwers, <hi>That the Providence of God alters no Legal Rights, nor forbids thoſe who are diſpoſſeſt of them to recover them if they can. While ſuch a Prince is in the Throne, it is a Declaration of God's Will that he ſhall reign for ſome time, longer or ſhorter, as God pleaſes;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96693:11"/>and that is an Obligation to Subjects to ſubmit: but that one Prince is at preſent plac'd in the Throne, and the other remov'd out of it, does not prove that it is Gods Will it ſhould be always ſo, and therefore does not diveſt the diſpoſſeſt Prince of his Legal Right, and Claim, nor forbid him to endeavour to recover his Throne, nor forbid thoſe, who are under no Obligation to the Prince in Poſſeſſion, to aſſiſt the diſpoſſeſſed Prince to recover his Legal right.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I reply,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Doctor owns that the diſpoſſeſs'd Prince, who had God's Authority, has loſt it; and methinks he ſhould own too, that he has loſt his Legal Right; for either the Authority muſt ſtay with the Legal Right, or the Legal Right muſt go away with the Authority; unleſs the Doctor will ſay that God Almighty has not Authority to deprive a Prince of his Legal Right. And if ſo, I ask the Doctor, From whom did the Prince, now diſpoſſeſſed, receive his Legal Right? from God, or the People? From the People he will not ſay, for fear I ſhould bring him to renounce another Principle. He muſt then ſay that the Prince deriv'd his Legal Title from God; And why may not God, who gave him a Legal Right, take it from him? And how is he ſure that he has not? How does he know that Gods Providence alters no Legal Rights? God may alter Legal Rights if he pleaſes, and that he does not, or will not, is more than he can tell. The Legal Right therefore ſeems to me to be loſt according to the Doctor's Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. But,</p>
               <p n="2">2. Suppoſe the diſpoſſeſſed Prince ſtill to retain his Legal Right; I ask, Is his Legal Right the ſame that it was before he was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed? Yes, he will ſay, <hi>for the Providence of God alters no Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Rights.</hi> Has he then a Right to every thing that he had a Right to when he was in Poſſeſſion? Yes, ſays he, for otherwiſe the Legal Right would not be the ſame as it was. I ask then, whether he has a Right to the Allegiance of his Subjects? No, ſays he, that is due now to another; that is to be paid to him who has God's Authority: Then, ſay I, the Legal Right either is quite gone, or at leaſt it is not the ſame; for before he was diſpoſſeſſed, his Legal Right did entitle him to the Allegiance of his Subjects, now it does not. The Legal Right therefore ſignifies nothing, and entitles him to nothing.</p>
               <p>And what will it ſignify to have a Right to his Crown, if his Subjects are under an Obligation not to aſſiſt him?
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96693:12"/>Why, all the Comfort that he gives his Legal King, is this, he tells him
<hi>that God does not forbid him to recover his Legal Right, nor forbids thoſe who are under no Obligation to the Prince in Poſſeſſion, to aſſiſt him to recover his Legal Right.</hi> ...But he muſt expect no Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from his Subjects, for indeed they are none of his Subjects now, tho he has ſtill a Legal Right to be their King.</p>
               <p>I will deſire the Doctor to view this Matter in a like Caſe, that he may ſee the abſurdity of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> lays claim to certain Lands which are in the Poſſeſſion of <hi>B,</hi> and in order to the Recovery of them ſues <hi>B</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall;</hi> brings his Writings and Deeds into Court, and deſires they may be read; brings his Witneſſes, and prays that they may be heard. The Judge tells him plainly, that 'tis needleſs to read over his Deeds, and examine his Writings, and hear his Witneſſes; that this will but perplex the Controverſy, and diſtract the Jury, and trouble the Court to no purpoſe; and that he has a readier way to decide the Matter: and then, immediately, without hearing the Cauſe, gives his Inſtructions to the Jury: Look you, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, here is a Queſtion about certain Lands, which <hi>A</hi> claims, but <hi>B</hi> poſſeſſes; where the Legal Right is, whether in <hi>A,</hi> or <hi>B,</hi> we know not; nor does it concern us to enquire. It is plain, that wherever the Legal Right is, the Poſſeſſion is in <hi>B,</hi> and you need enquire no further: And therefore you ought to find for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendent. 'Tis the Will of God it ſhould be ſo, his Providence has ſo appointed it, and we muſt obey. But, mark you, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, in caſe that <hi>A</hi> ſhould have the Legal Right, (which I ſay belongs not at all to you to enquire) your finding for
<hi>B</hi> does not take away from <hi>A</hi> his Legal Right: It is plain that the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God has remov'd <hi>A</hi> from the Poſſeſſion of his Lands, and has given them to
<hi>B;</hi> but that alters no Legal Rights, nor forbids <hi>A</hi> who is diſpoſſeſſed of his Lands, to recover them if he can. While <hi>B,</hi> is in Poſſeſſion of them, it is a plain Declaration of God's Will that he ſhall have them for ſome time, longer or ſhorter, as God pleaſes; and that is ſufficient Warrant for you to find for <hi>B.</hi> But that
<hi>B</hi> is at preſent in Poſſeſſion of theſe Lands, and <hi>A</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of them, does not prove it to be God's Will it ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſo; and therefore it does not diveſt <hi>A</hi> of his Legal Right and Claim, nor forbid him to endeavour to recover his Lands, nor forbid the <hi>Mob</hi> (who are under no Obligation to Uſurpers and Invaders of other Mens Rights and Properties, and are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways kind to and ready to help injur'd Perſons) to aſſiſt
<hi>A</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96693:12"/>his Legal Right. For, Gentlemen, let me tell you, Legal Right is the ordinary way, whereby the Providence of God diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of Lands, and this bars all other humane Claims; but yet God may give the Lands of <hi>A</hi> to <hi>B</hi> if he pleaſes; but this does not deſtroy the Legal Right of <hi>A,</hi> who is depriv'd of his Lands, nor hinder him from raiſing the <hi>Mob</hi> to eject <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vi &amp; A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m's.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the very Doctrine that this Author teaches; and if this be not Enthuſiaſm, I know not what is. One would admire that any Man, who converſes ſo much with Lawyers, ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance ſuch a Doctrine which deſtroys all our Laws, and unſettles our Civil Rights and Properties, and tends to nothing but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion: For if this Doctrine be true that he teaches, the Lawyers may fling away their Law-Books, and ſhut up <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>-Hall; for why ſhould Clients come to them for Advice, if this were the beſt Advice they could give, that they ſhould raiſe as great a Force as they can to recover their Legal Rights? for this might have been done without conſulting of them. Surely the Lawyers will con him no Thanks for this Book: But what does he care? he is above the Lawyers, and above the Law too; and by his own Authority, join'd with that of the Convocation, can repeal all our Laws, and null Acts of Parliament, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that whatever the Law or Cuſtom has hitherto been, yet for the future Poſſeſſion alone ſhall give Right.</p>
               <p>Nay, by this Doctor's Principles, a Murderer is the Miniſter of God, and ought to be cleared in any of the King's Courts. For let us ſuppoſe <hi>B</hi> to be murdered, and <hi>A</hi> to have been the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer. I will by the Doctor's Principles teach <hi>A</hi> how he ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelf. <hi>A</hi> therefore ſhall own the Fact, that he did really kill <hi>B;</hi> but he had an Impulſe from God ſo to do; and this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe was equivalent to a Divine Command, and a Divine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is a ſufficient Warrant for any Man to ſend another out of the World. The Judg interrogates him further, how he can prove that he had an Impulſe from God? 'Tis plain, ſays
<hi>A,</hi> that this Impulſe was from God, becauſe without his Power I could not have done it, and God never intruſts any Man with power to kill another, unleſs he give him Authority to do it. So that Providence is the Murderer and not I. The Judg then, well inſtructed in Dr.
<hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Principles, tells the Jury, that here is one of our Sovereign Lord the King's Subjects murder'd, and that <hi>A</hi> owns he did it; but they muſt bring him in <hi>Not Guilty,</hi> becauſe though he did kill the Man, yet he did it with God's Authority.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:96693:13"/>
               <p>I dread to mention the horrid and blaſphemous conſequences of this fanatical and enthuſiaſtical Doctrine: for hereby all Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies, and Thefts, and Murders, and Maſſacres, every thing that is abominable both to God and Man, will be charg'd on God. And this is a ſufficient Argument that it cannot be true.</p>
               <p n="2">II. I will borrow another Objection of Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s, and that is this; <hi>Have not Pirats and Robbers as good a Title to my Purſe, as an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper has to the Crown, which he ſeizes by as manifeſt Force and Violence? Does not the Providence of God order and diſpoſe all theſe Events? And are we not bound then as much to ſubmit to Pirats, as to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which he gives this Anſwer, <hi>The diſpute is not about Humane and Legal Right in either Caſe.</hi> True, for neither has a Robber any legal Title to my Purſe, nor has an Uſurper any legal Right to the Crown; <hi>but the diſpute is about Authority, which is the only reaſon of a conſcientious Subjection.</hi> But what, I beſeech him, is this Authority, which he ſays the Diſpute is about? is it Humane and Legal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority? No, for that is the ſame with Humane and Legal Right. <hi>It is,</hi> he tells us, <hi>God's Authority. Now no Man,</hi> ſays he,
<hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends that Thieves and Pirats have God's Authority, to which we muſt ſubmit.</hi> And I wonder that any Man ſhould pretend that Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers have God's Authority, to which we muſt ſubmit. God's Authority is a Divine Right: Now I think an Uſurper has no more a Divine Right to ſeize the Publick Treaſure of a Nation, and to take a thouſand thouſand Purſes at once, than a Robber has to take one Purſe; and I am no more in Conſcience bound to ſubmit to an Uſurper, and not to reſiſt him, than I am bound to ſubmit to a Robber, and tamely to deliver my Purſe to him. I beſeech him to tell me, why Tyrants and Uſurpers have a Divine Right to their ſtollen Goods, but Robbers and Pirats have it not? The Reaſon he aſſures us is this, <hi>The Scripture ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly tells us, that Kingdoms are diſpos'd by God.</hi> And I ask him, Are not Mens Purſes, and Mony, and Goods at his diſpoſal? Are not all Things his? And who ſhall diſpoſe of what is his, but himſelf? Does God diſpoſe only of Crowns and Scepters, and leave leſſer Matters to be diſpos'd of by others? As there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he thus argues,
<hi>All Power is of God, and therefore whenever any Prince, by what unjuſt means ſoever with reſpect to Men, is plac'd in the Throne, and ſettled there, he is advanc'd by God, is God's Ordinance, God's Miniſter, and muſt be obey'd for Conſcience-ſake.</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:96693:14"/>So in like manner I will argue according to his Principles thus: All Riches are of God,<note place="margin">1 Chron. 29.12.</note> 
                  <hi>(for Riches and Honours come of him)</hi> And therefore when any Robber, by what unjuſt means ſoever with reſpect to Men, gets Riches, he is enriched by God, is God's Steward, and God has but taken away the Stewardſhip from another, and given it to him; and he may as properly call the Goods he has unjuſtly gotten, his own, as the former Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard could, when they were in his keeping. And therefore <hi>the Outrages of Pirats and Thieves are</hi> not <hi>impertinently alledg'd in this Cauſe. They have,</hi> ſays he,
<hi>Force and Violence, which every Man muſt ſubmit to, when he cannot help it.</hi> And what elſe have Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, but Force and Violence, which every Man muſt ſubmit to, when he cannot help it? O, he tells us, <hi>Sovereign Power is God's Authority, though Princes may be advanced to it by no honeſter Means, than Thieves take a Purſe.</hi> I ask him, Does he think that a Prince, who is advanc'd to Sovereign Power by no hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Means than Thieves take a Purſe, has any Divine Right to his Crown? Yes, he will ſay, becauſe God has given him a Crown. But how has God given him a Crown? He will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, by <hi>the diſpoſals of his Providence.</hi> In like manner may I ſay, that a Robber has a Divine Right to his ill-gotten Goods, for God has given them to him by <hi>the diſpoſals of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whereas he ſays, <hi>The beginnings of the four firſt Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies were no better, and yet their Power was of God;</hi> I may with full as much reaſon ſay, that the beginnings of ſome poor and mean Robbers, who afterwards grow Rich by ſpoiling others, are not one jot worſe than the unjuſt beginnings of the four Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies; and therefore their unjuſtly-gotten Wealth is of God. I will undertake to make out, that Thieves have as much Divine Right to their ſtollen Goods, as any Uſurper has to his Crown. But to puſh the Matter further.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Suppoſe that <hi>A</hi> has unjuſtly gotten the Government into his Hands, and by Force and Violence ſettled himſelf in it, and conſequently, according to his Doctrine, has got God Almighty's Authority. I ask the Doctor, who gave <hi>A</hi> Authority to get God Almighty's Authority into his Hands? Will he ſay, God gave him Authority to get God Almighty's Authority? If ſo, then <hi>A</hi> did not ſin; for no Man ſins that acts by God's Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and yet he did ſin, becauſe he us'd very unjuſt means to get God's Authority, Will he ſay, that Man gave him Authority to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96693:15"/>get God's Authority into his Hands? Then Man gave him Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to ſin againſt God, (for I ſuppoſe he gets God's Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity by unjuſt means.) but no Man can do this; no Man can give another what he has not himſelf, for no Man has Authority to ſin againſt God.</p>
               <p>We have thus brought our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> to the Steps of the Royal Throne, without any Authority; but now we muſt change his Name, and call him <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> no longer; tho he aſcended the Throne an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> yet he is no ſooner in it, but he is <hi>God's Ordinance, God's Miniſter, God's Lieutenant, God's Vicegerent, God's Anointed.</hi> He was, whilſt he made his way to the Throne, an unjuſt Oppreſſor, and a Murderer, for he waded through Blood to it: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a ſudden Converſion, a wonderful Change wrought on him; a wonderful Change indeed, like that of Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for though he be made God's Vicegerent, and has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from him a Commiſſion to be his Miniſter for the Good of his People; yet ſtill he is, what he was before, a Devil. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him ſitting upon the Royal Throne, with a Crown on his Head, and a Scepter in his Hand, full of Majeſty, and having God's Authority to beſtow Biſhopricks and Deaneries on thoſe of the Clergy that flatter him, and to kill and murder the Laity as faſt as he pleaſes. Dr. <hi>Hicks</hi> immediately haſtens to Court; and leſt the new Prince ſhould commit a miſtake in governing according to the
<hi>Political Law,</hi> he inſtructs him in the Nature and full Extent of his <hi>Imperial Law,</hi> and preſents <hi>Jovian</hi> to him. Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> comes next, and acquaints his Sacred Majeſty, that he has God's Authority, which is always irreſiſtible; and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with preſenteth his two Caſes, the one of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> &amp;c. the other of
<hi>Reſiſtance,</hi> &amp;c. But he wiſely takes care to blot out that Paſſage in his Caſe of Reſiſtance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> P. 128. <hi>That when St.</hi> Paul <hi>ſays, All Power is of God, he means only Legal Power;</hi> for the Book with that Paſſage in it would be a very unfit Preſent for an Uſurper.</p>
               <p>Next comes <hi>the Guide of the Inferior Clergy,</hi> and aſſures his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, that he is ready to ſerve him with Tongue and Pen, and promiſes the ſame in the Name of all his Scholars. Then come the Addreſſers from Cities and Corporations, and theſe tender their Lives, and Fortunes, and Obedience, without reſerve. The Diſpenſing Judges bring up the Rear; and theſe bring the Body of the Laws in their Hands, and lay them at his Majeſty's Feet, aſſuring him, that (notwithſtanding whatever <hi>Bracton,</hi> and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96693:15"/>
                  <hi>Forteſcue,</hi> and other famous Lawyers have ſaid to the contrary) he is above the Law, and may if he liſt rule without it. And now, if we will take Dr.
<hi>Sherlock</hi>'s word for it, the Uſurper is <hi>ſettled in his Throne, the whole<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Adminiſtration of the Government, and the whole Power of the Nation is in his Hands; every thing is done in his Name, and by his Authority,</hi> (tho, as I have ſhew'd, Authority he has none)
<hi>the great Body of the Nation has ſubmitted to him, and thoſe who will not ſubmit can be cruſh'd by him whenever he pleaſes:</hi> This, this is his Right and Title to the Crown,
<hi>that he can cruſh thoſe who will not ſubmit, whenever he pleaſes. And if this be not a ſettled Government, he deſpairs of ever knowing what it is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſtill all this is nothing but Force and Violence, there is no Authority: For the Uſurper has no more God's Authority now he ſits on the Throne, than he had before he aſcended it; Power and Authority are not the ſame; for though all Authority be Power, yet all Power is not Authority; and though it ſhould grow or ſwell never ſo much, yet it cannot grow and ſwell into Authority; ſtill it will be Force and Power, and no more.</p>
               <p>True ſays the Doctor, I grant that Power cannot give Right and Authority to govern, (for that is <hi>Hobbiſm,</hi> and he is no <hi>Hobbiſt</hi>)<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>But,</hi> ſays he, <hi>'tis a certain ſign, that where-ever God has plac'd the Power, he has given the Authority.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>For ſince Power will govern, God ſo orders it by his Providence, as never to intruſt Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Power in any Man's hands, to whom he does not give Sovereign Authority.</hi> Now here indeed is the pinch of the Matter, and therefore I ſhall endeavour to eaſe my ſelf and my Reader of it.</p>
               <p>The Doctor allows, that Sovereign Power is not Sovereign Authority, and herein we agree:
<hi>But,</hi> ſays he, <hi>it is a certain ſign, that where God has plac'd the Sovereign Power, he has given the Authority.</hi> But this I deny, and thus I argue againſt it.</p>
               <p>Power is not a certain ſign of Authority, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sovereign Power is not a certain ſign of Sovereign Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; for 'tis every jot as reaſonable, that Power ſhould be a ſign of ſome Authority given by God to him who has the Power, as it is that Sovereign Power ſhould be a certain ſign of Sovereign Authority. For as the Doctor argues, <hi>Since Power will govern, God ſo orders it by his Providence, as never to intruſt Sovereign Power in any Man's hands, to whom he gives not Sovereign
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96693:16"/>Authority.</hi> So in like manner do I argue: Since all Power, though it be leſs than Sovereign, will govern as far as it can; that is, will give Law to, and domineer over thoſe that have leſs Power, and will oppreſs and cruſh them, (which is, in the Doctor's ſenſe, to govern) God ſo orders it by his Providence, as never to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt any Power in any Man's hands, to whom he does not give ſome Authority: And the Conſequence of this is, that every one who is ſtronger than Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> has Authority to govern him; for God, it ſeems, would not have given him ſufficient Power to govern the Doctor, unleſs he had annex'd Authority thereto. And this, if it be not <hi>Hobbiſm,</hi> yet is ſo like to it, that it is not eaſy for any one who has not Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s ſubtilty, to diſtinguiſh it from
<hi>Hobbiſm.</hi> I cannot think the Doctor will allow that any one who has Power to govern him, has alſo Authority; and yet by his Principles he ought to allow it. For whatever Reaſon he will aſſign, why, <hi>Since Power will govern, God ſo orders it by his Providence, as never to intruſt Sovereign Power in the hands of any Man to whom he does not give Sovereign Authority;</hi> Whatever Reaſon he will or can aſſign for this, will ſerve me for a Reaſon to prove that God does not, or according to the Doctor's principle, ſhould not intruſt any Power, though leſs than Sovereign, in the hands of any Man, to whom he does not give ſome Authority in proportion to it. So that if this Argument of his proves any thing, the fault of it is, that it proves too much; for if it proves what he would have, that God gives Authority to Tyrants, it proves alſo what he would not, that God gives Authority to all Oppreſſors. Methinks ſuch a ſtartling Aſſertion as this, ſhould have been prov'd by our Author, he ought to have given ſome reaſon for it, for all Men will not take it upon his Authority. But ſince he has given us no reaſon for it, I will examine what colour of reaſon there may be for it, for a good reaſon there can be none. If God ſo orders matters, as never to entruſt Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Power in the hands of any Man to whom he does not give Sovereign Authority, the moſt likely reaſon of it is this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Sovereign Power may do a great deal of miſchief in the World; and 'tis not agreeable to a wiſe and juſt and good God, to permit that any one ſhould have ſuch a Power without his Authority annexed to it.</p>
               <p>Now to this I anſwer;</p>
               <p n="1">1. They who have Sovereign Power without God's Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, are as much under the Reſtraint and Government of God,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96693:16"/>as they who have Sovereign Power with his Authority: and therefore God can prevent and ſtop the proudeſt of Uſurpers and Tyrants from doing all the miſchief they intend; and ſo he does, whenever ſo to do will tend moſt to the honour of his own Name, and to the good of his People; for a mighty Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, how great ſoever his Power is, is but the
<hi>Rod of God's An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> (as it was ſaid of <hi>Sennacherib</hi>) and God ſurely has the hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Rod:</hi> And whether the <hi>Rod</hi> ſhall draw Blood or no, depends on the Pleaſure of him that holds it. He is God's <hi>Axe,</hi> and whether the <hi>Axe</hi> ſhall cut or no, depends on the Will of him that has it in his Hands, and may or may not hew therewith.<note place="margin">Iſa. 10.15.</note> And <hi>ſhall the Axe boaſt it ſelf againſt him that heweth therewith? Or ſhall the Saw magnify it ſelf againſt him that ſhaketh it? As if the Rod<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhould ſhake it ſelf againſt them that lift it up? Or as if the Staff ſhould lift up it ſelf, as if it were no Wood.</hi> Such mean, and weak, and contemptible things, are the greateſt and proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Uſurpers and Tyrants, when compar'd with God. The pretence therefore, that Sovereign Power is capable of doing a great deal of Miſchief and Evil in the World (as indeed it is) can be no reaſon why God ſhould never ſuffer it to be lodg'd in the hands of any one, to whom he gives not Sovereign Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, becauſe he can check and reſtrain the Power of Uſurpers and Tyrants as he pleaſes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The annexing of Sovereign Authority to Sovereign Power, will not hinder thoſe who have the Authority from abuſing their Power, and going beyond their Authority. And therefore this Conſideration, that Sovereign Power is capable of doing a great deal of Evil and Miſchief in the World, is no reaſon why we ſhould ſay that God gives Sovereign Authority with it; becauſe Sovereign Power, whether with or without Authority, is equally capable of doing miſchief; for 'tis the Man himſelf that does miſchief, and not the Power, though indeed he could not do ſo much miſchief without ſo much Power; and 'tis the Grace of God that muſt reſtrain him from doing miſchief, and not his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If this were a good reaſon why God ſhould never intruſt Sovereign Power in any Man's hands, to whom he gives not So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Authority, it would likewiſe ſerve for a reaſon why he ſhould not intruſt a leſs than Sovereign Power in any Man's hands to whom he does not give ſome Authority; and yet we find that he, in the courſe of his Providence, does intruſt leſs than
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96693:17"/>Sovereign Power in the hands of thoſe to whom he gives no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: As the Power that every Oppreſſor has, is from God, but God ſurely gives him no Authority to oppreſs.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. But let us ſuppoſe now that whoever has Sovereign Power, has alſo Sovereign Authority, and muſt not be reſiſted, and then I will prove, that the Sovereign Authority is always in the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; for bare Sovereign Power is only Sovereign Force, and Sovereign Force is the greateſt natural Strength; and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the greateſt ſtrength is in the People, if the Doctor will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me that five or ſix Millions of Men have more ſtrength than one ſingle Man who is ſeated on the Throne. Nay, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Principle, Sovereign Authority can never be any where elſe but in the People; becauſe the People cannot part with their ſtrength, nor confer it on the Supream Magiſtrate; it is ſo their own, that they cannot give it away. But you'l ſay, they may promiſe, that they will not uſe their natural ſtrength otherwiſe than the Supream Magiſtrate, or than the Law ſhall direct. True; but though they promiſe that they will not uſe their natural ſtrength otherwiſe than the Law directs, yet ſtill they retain it; nor are they, upon their making of ſuch a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, weaker than they were before, there being not the leaſt abatement of their natural ſtrength: So that if they had Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Power before they made ſuch a Promiſe, it follows that they have it ſtill. And therefore if (as he ſays) <hi>Power be a certain ſign to us, that where God has plac'd the Power, he has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Authority;</hi> It is infallibly true, that the Authority is in the People, and can be no where elſe, becauſe there God has plac'd the Power.</p>
               <p>Hence I obſerve,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Doctor is really no Friend to crowned Heads, for he has unking'd them all; he has taken away from them their Sovereign Authority, and given it to the People. Now ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that an oppreſſed People ſhould be ſenſible that they have the ſuperior Strength, and ſhould be ſo cunning as from thence to conclude with the Doctor, that they have God's Authority to deliver themſelves from the Yoke of the Oppreſſor; I think, according to his Principles, he ought to allow, they have Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to free themſelves from Oppreſſion, becauſe they have Power, Supream Power, or ſtrength lodg'd in them; and <hi>God never intruſts Sovereign Power in any Man's (or Mens) hands, to whom he does not give Sovereign Authority.</hi> Beſides it may be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96693:17"/>conſider'd, that though, when they ſee an Uſurper on the Throne, they ſhould with the Doctor conclude it to be <hi>God's Will, that he ſhould reign for ſome time longer or ſhorter as God pleaſes:</hi> Yet they are taught by the Doctor, <hi>That this does not prove it to be God's Will it ſhould be always ſo.</hi> And therefore when they find they have ſtrength to reſiſt the Tyrant, and can agree together to make uſe of it, they will preſently conclude, that it is not God's Will that they ſhould be Slaves one Week or Day longer. And thus the Doctor's Tyrant is on a ſudden tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled down from his Royal Throne by that very Argument, that he made uſe of to ſet him up.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Doctor is fallen out with the Univerſity of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> who condemn'd this Principle, <hi>That all Civil Authority is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd originally from the People;</hi> and if the Fires be ſtill continued there, his Book will be in ſome danger. Nay, he is all on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fallen out with himſelf; and from being a mighty Aſſertor of the Prerogatives and Rights of Kings, is become a Republi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can: And who can doubt but for the future, <hi>Lex Rex, Vindiciae contra Tyrannos, Milton</hi>'s <hi>Defenſio populi Anglicani,</hi> and ſuch-like Books, will be in great eſteem with him.</p>
               <p>But this is only a ſlip of the Doctor; he ſtill means well to Kings, eſpecially if they be ſuch as he ſets up.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>England,</hi> behold the King that Doctor <hi>Sherlock</hi> gives thee! he is an abſolute Lord, and ſome will call him Tyrant. For,</p>
               <p n="5">V. He that is a Sovereign Prince, and has God's Authority but no Legal Right, is an abſolute and unlimited Monarch; and conſequently ſuch a King as <hi>England</hi> never yet own'd; for it is Law that ſets bounds to Regal Power; and therefore he that is our King, but not by Law, is an abſolute and unlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Monarch. And I am ſure whatever Notions ſome Men, who underſtand little of our Laws, have concerning the boundleſs Power and uncontroulable Authority of Kings, yet the Laws do really bound the Regal Power; this the Lawyers teach us: This is the Doctrine of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>-Hall. And I think in a matter of this nature, it is more reaſonable to take the Judgment of Lawyers than of Divines.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. He that has God's Authority without any Legal Right, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be limited by Laws: For God's Authority cannot be limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Men; and therefore if it be true, that he who has no le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Right to govern, has God's Authority when he is ſettled in the Throne, then it follows that he has an Authority that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96693:18"/>be bounded by humane Laws. For a Power that God gives none can ſet bounds to, beſides God; and if he has made no limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the Regal Power, (as 'tis plain he has not, juſt as plain as it is that he has ſaid nothing about it) then no limitations can be made: ſuch a King cannot yield that any limits ſhould be ſet to God's Authority which he is inveſted with, unleſs he ſhould have a new Authority from Heaven impowring him to do ſo: And the People cannot ſet bounds to it, neither with nor without his Conſent; not without the King's Conſent, for that would be rebelling againſt God's Vicegerent, and trampling on Divine Authority, that would be no leſs than a robbing of God, a ſtealing of God's Authority, and the worſt of Sacriledges: nor can they ſet bounds to his Power with his Conſent; for if he cannot part with any of his Power, they cannot take it, for that would be like receiving of ſtollen Goods.</p>
               <p>Beſides, it may be conſidered, that ſurely God gives a Prince no more of his Authority, than is fit and neceſſary to ſerve the Ends of Government; and therefore he cannot part with any of it; or if he ſhould, he would not have enough left him to ſerve the Ends of Government; at leaſt he could not be ſure that he ſhould have enough, unleſs he were alſo ſure of this, that God at firſt gave him more than enough; which he cannot be certain of. He may indeed know that he has more than he needs for his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Occaſions; but he does not know how ſoon the Scene of Affairs may change; and then all <hi>God's Authority,</hi> even the whole <hi>Imperial Law</hi> may be little enough for him.</p>
               <p>I have as much Zeal and dutiful Affection for their Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties, King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> as any of my fellow-Subjects; and as I believe them to have as good a Title to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> as any of their Royal Anceſtors ever had; ſo I hope they are ſo firmly ſettled in the Throne, that all the Powers on Earth will not be able to remove them. But I think Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> does by his Principles undermine their Throne; for though he <hi>inveſts them with God's Authority, becauſe they have the Sovereign Power, are able to cruſh whom they pleaſe, and are ſettled in the Throne;</hi> yet he will not own them to have a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Right to ſit thereon; whereas it is moſt certain, that there is nothing can ſecure to a Prince his Sovereign Power, but that which ſets bounds to it, the Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:96693:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> Wherein is ſhew'd how little value we ought to have for the Acts and Canons of the Convocation, begun in the firſt Year of King <hi>James I. 1603.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOR, to the Authority of the Convocation begun in the firſt Year of King <hi>James</hi> I, I may oppoſe the Authority of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Convocations in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> wherein the Biſhops and Clergy were of a contrary Opinion. I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in two only, the one in the 35th, and the other in the 39th Year of that Queen's Reign.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the 35th of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Clergy were of Opinion, that an Uſurper, though ſettled in the Throne, had not God's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and no Allegiance was due to him, as appears plainly from their granting the Queen two Subſidies of four Shillings in the Pound, to aſſiſt the <hi>Dutch</hi> in ſhaking off their Obedience to their once Sovereign the King of <hi>Spain.</hi> 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> c. 12. <hi>The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates and Clergy of the Province of</hi> Canterbury <hi>have, for certain Conſiderations, lovingly and liberally given and granted to the Queen's moſt excellent Majesty two Subſidies of Four Shillings in the Pound.</hi> What were thoſe Conſiderations? Amongſt others this was one, <hi>The conſideration of her Majeſty's great Charges in the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and needful prevention of ſuch intended Attempts as manifeſtly tended to the utter overthrow of the preſent happy ſtate of her High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs's Realm, to the miſerable ruin of divers other Princes and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries aſſociate and near adjoining, and to the extirpation and rooting out of the ſincere profeſſion of the Goſpel both here and elſewhere.</hi> The Temporalities Subſidy-Act explains this to us in theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for their Tax, <hi>Cap.</hi> 13. <hi>"Beſides the great and perpetual Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which it has pleaſed God to give your Majeſty abroad, in making You the principal Support of all juſt and religious Cauſes againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers: So that this Iſland has in your Majesty's Days been as a Stay and Sanctuary to diſtreſſed States and Kingdoms, and as a Bulwark againſt the Tyranny of mighty and uſurping Potentates.—Beſides the great Succours in</hi> France <hi>and</hi> Flanders, <hi>which we do conceive to be moſt Honourable, in regard of the Ancient Leagues, the Juſtice and Equity of their Cauſes,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe were the chief Reaſons that moved the Clergy to give four Shillings in the Pound to the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96693:19"/>Queen. This was read a third time, (<hi>Mar.</hi> 30.1593.) in the Lords Houſe, theſe following Biſhops being preſent, and no <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientes</hi> among them, as appears from the Journals of the Lords Houſe.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cantuarienſis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Londinenſis.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Godwin</hi> de Praeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aſaphenſis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Roffenſis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Exonienſis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ciceſtrenſis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Licolnienſis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Petroburgenſis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Herefordenſis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bangorenſis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Wigornienſis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Landavenſis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sarisburienſis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bathonenſ. &amp; Wellenſis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Johames Whitgift.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Johan. Elmer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gulielmus Hughes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Johannes Young.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Johannes Woolton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Bickley.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gulielmus Wickham.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richardus Howland.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Herbert Westfaling.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hugo Bellott.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richardus Fletcher.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gervaſius Babington.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richardus Coldwell.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Johannes Still.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Now I think it is plain from hence, that the Biſhops and Clergy, in the 35th of Queen
<hi>Elizabeth,</hi> did believe that an U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurper, though he be ſettled in the Throne, has not God's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and that thoſe who are oppreſs'd by him, may lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſiſt him, and free themſelves from his Yoke; for had they been of Opinion that it was a Sin in the Dutch to reſiſt <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>2d</hi> King of <hi>Spain,</hi> as having God's Authority; would they not have directed her Majeſty's Conſcience better in this Matter? would they not have humbly repreſented to her Highneſs, that though <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>2d</hi> was an Uſurper, yet he had God's Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and therefore neither ought his Subjects to reſiſt him, nor ſhe to aſſiſt them in making reſiſtance? Would they not have given her Sacred Majeſty good <hi>Advice</hi> rather than <hi>Mony?</hi> Would they not have admoniſhed the Dutch to lay down their Arms, and fly to their <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Tears?</hi> Who can think they would have been ſo uncharitable to their Proteſtant Neighbours, as to ſet forward their Damnation, or ſo fooliſh as to buy their own at the rate of Four Shillings in the Pound? Such Actions as theſe do plainly ſhew what Opinion Arch-Biſhop <hi>Whitgift,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<hi>Elmer,</hi> and the reſt of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Biſhops and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy had concerning this Matter; and that as plainly as the Acts
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:96693:19"/>and Canons of a Convocation.</p>
               <p>It may here be very proper to conſider, that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> had once a Legal Right to govern the Dutch, who were his Subjects, and ow'd him Allegiance; but the Prelats and Clergy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> did verily believe he had forfeited and loſt it by uſurping upon them; (for it ſeems, they were of Opinion, that a Prince might uſurp upon his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, as well as Subjects upon their Prince) and this I believe was our Caſe, King <hi>James</hi> the
<hi>2d</hi> having been that to us, which <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>2d</hi> was to the Dutch.</p>
               <p>That which I gather from hence, is this, That Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi>'s Biſhops, either did not think that an Uſurper was inveſted with God's Authority; or if they did, they believed it lawful in ſome Caſes to reſiſt a Prince though inveſted with God's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. Now let Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> chuſe which of the two he will grant me, for I think it cannot be avoided but one of the two muſt be allow'd.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the 39th of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Chap. 26. The Clergy think themſelves bound,
<hi>&amp;c, to offer unto her Highneſs as a Teſtimony and Token of their good Wills and dutiful Affections, ſome ſuch Aid and Contribution towards the ſupportation of her Majeſties Charges, as they are perſwaded the greatneſs of the ſame moſt juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may require.</hi> And the Temporalities Subſidy-Act, 39 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 27. has theſe words; <hi>This Land is become, ſince your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti's happy Days, both a Port and a Haven of Refuge for diſtreſſed States and Kingdoms, and a Rock and Bulwark of Oppoſition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Tyrannies and ambitious Attempts of mighty and uſurping Potentates.</hi> This paſs'd the Houſe of Lords <hi>Dec.</hi> 19. 1596; fourteen Biſhops being preſent and agreeing to it, one of which was Arch-Biſhop <hi>Whitgift,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The concluſion from hence is eaſy, that in the 39th of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s reign the Prelates and Clergy own'd not this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers, when ſettled in the Throne, are inveſted with God</hi>'s <hi>Authority, and muſt be obey'd by all thoſe who live within their Territories and Dominions, as well Prieſts as People.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, it ought to be conſider'd, that the Acts and Canons of this Convocation wherein Dr.
<hi>Overall</hi> was Prolocutor, were never ratified in Parliament.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:96693:20"/>
               <p>But you will ſay, They however give us the Judgment of the then Church of
<hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer;</p>
               <p n="1">1. That here is Church againſt Church, and Convocation againſt Convocation, nay two Convocations (and I might have ſaid, four) in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign againſt one in the Reign of her immediate Succeſſor, K. <hi>James.</hi> Now methinks the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of two or more Convocations in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, ſhould outweigh the Authority of one ſingle Convocation in the reign of King <hi>James;</hi> unleſs it can be made out, that the Church grows wiſer and better every Age and every Year than other, which I make ſome doubt of.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Head of the Church agreed with the Members; for both the Queen and her Convocations were of Opinion, that 'twas lawful for the
<hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> to ſhake off their Obedience to their once Sovereign King <hi>Philip;</hi> but in the following reign of King <hi>James,</hi> the Head of the Church and the Members differ'd about this Point, and the King was on the <hi>Hollander</hi>'s ſide; as appears from a Letter which that King wrote to Dr. <hi>Abbot;</hi> Part of which I have thought fit to tranſcribe.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>
                           <hi>Good Dr.</hi> Abbot,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <q>
                        <p>I Cannot abſtain to give you my Judgment of your Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in your Convocation,<note place="margin">New Obſ. Vol. <hi>3.</hi> Numb. <hi>22.</hi>
                           </note> as you call it;—You know all of you, as I think, that my Reaſon of calling you together, was to give your Judgments how far a Chriſtian and a Proteſtant King, may concur to aſſiſt his Neighbours to ſhake off their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to their once Sovereign, upon the Account of Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, Tyranny, or what elſe you like to name it. In the late Queen<hi>'s</hi> time, this Kingdom was very free in aſſiſting the <hi>Hollanders</hi> both with Arms and Advice. And none of your Coat ever told me, that any ſcrupled about it in her Reign. Upon my coming to <hi>England,</hi> you may know that it came from ſome of your ſelves to raiſe Scruples about this Matter. —Yet I never took any notice of theſe Scruples, till the Affairs of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> forc'd me to it. All my Neighbours call on me to concur in the Treaty between <hi>Holland</hi> and
<hi>Spain;</hi> and the Honour of the Nation will not ſuffer the <hi>Hollanders</hi> to be abandoned, eſpecially after ſo much Money and Men ſpent in their Quarrel: Therefore I was of the Mind to call
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:96693:20"/>my Clergy together, to ſatisfy not ſo much me, as the World about us of the Juſtneſs of my owning the <hi>Hollanders</hi> at this time: This I needed not have done; and you have forced me to ſay, I wiſh I had not. You have dipp'd too deep in what all Kings reſerve among the <hi>Arcana Imperii.</hi> And whatever Averſion you may profeſs againſt God's being the Author of Sin, you have ſtumbled upon the Threſhold of that Opinion, in ſaying upon the Matter, that even Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is God's Authority, and ſhould be reverenc'd as ſuch. If the King of <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould return to claim his old Pontifical Right to my Kingdom, you leave me to ſeek for others to fight for it: For you tell us upon the Matter beforehand, his Authority is God's Authority, if he prevail.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Doctor, I have no time to expreſs my Mind farther in this thorny buſineſs. I ſhall give you my Orders about it by Mr. Solicitor; and until then, meddle no more in it, for they are Edge-Tools, or rather like that Weapon, that's ſaid to cut with the one edge, and cure with the other. I commit you to God's Protection, good Doctor <hi>Abbot,</hi> and reſt,</p>
                     </q>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your good Friend, <hi>James</hi> R.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>And this I think leſſens the Authority of Dr. <hi>Overall</hi>'s Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation very much, that it is the Authority of a Church without a Head; for it is plain, that the Head of the Church is on my ſide. And I lay ſome weight on this, that King <hi>James</hi> who was a Sovereign Prince, and as fond of Power as any other, plainly told Dr. <hi>Abbot,</hi> that he ſcrupled not about the Lawfulneſs of what the <hi>Hollanders</hi> did in ſhaking off their Obedience to their once Sovereign the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> upon the account of his Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and Tyranny.</p>
               <p>Hence we may gather, that were K. <hi>James</hi> I. to judg between the late King his Grand-Son, and the People of <hi>England;</hi> he would ſurely give Judgment on the Peoples ſide; for he cannot condemn the People of <hi>England</hi> without condemning the Dutch: And his Judgment in this Caſe I think we ought to value more, than the Opinions of an hundred Doctors that differ from him.</p>
               <p>But 'tis time now to draw to a concluſion. The Cauſe I am engaged in, is God's Cauſe, and the King's and Queen's Cauſe, and the Peoples Cauſe: it is God's Cauſe, whom Dr.
<hi>Sherlock</hi> ſeems, by his Principles, to make the Author of Sin: for <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:96693:21"/>averſion he may profeſs againſt God's being the Author of Sin, he has ſtumbled upon the threſhold of that Opinion, in ſaying upon the Matter, that even Tyranny is God's Authority, and ſhould be reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renc'd as ſuch.</hi> And it is the King's and Queen's Cauſe, whom the Doctor ſuppoſes to be Uſurpers, though I do not ſay he has call'd them ſo. I know no neceſſity there was for his writing on this Argument; and much leſs for his reaſoning on the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of unjuſt Uſurpations; for here was no ſuch thing as Uſurpation, unleſs to defend our Civil Rights and Liberties, and Religion eſtabliſh'd by Law, muſt be call'd Uſurpation; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he will call an excellent Prince, who came to deliver us from Popery and Slavery, an Uſurper. And though it may be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to <hi>put the Caſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Preface.</note> as he ſays, <hi>at the worſt;</hi> yet methinks he ought not to have left it <hi>at the worſt;</hi> he ſhould not have let his Reader run away with this Opinion, that King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> have not a Legal Title to the Crown. And though he forbids his Reader to <hi>charge him with reflecting on the preſent Government,</hi> yet there is no intelligent Reader but muſt take his whole Book to be a Reflection upon it; and will conclude from his not declaring King <hi>William</hi> and Queen
<hi>Mary</hi> to have a Legal Right to the Crown, that he does not believe it: For a wiſe Man, I think, would have declar'd it, had he believ'd it; and Dr. <hi>Sherlock never gave any juſt occaſion to the World to mark him out for a Fool.</hi> And it is the Peoples Cauſe, I mean it is the Cauſe of all thoſe that are the King's and Queen's Loyal Subjects; for ſince he ſays, That <hi>all Sovereign Princes, who are ſettled in their Thrones, are plac'd there by God, and inveſted with his Authority, and therefore muſt be obey'd,</hi> even though they turn Uſurpers, and oppreſs their Subjects, and deſtroy the Fundamental Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of the Government; it is plain that he charges all thoſe who aſſiſted his Highneſs the Prince of
<hi>Orange,</hi> and were the ſubordinate Inſtruments of our Deliverance, with down-right Rebellion againſt the late King. And theſe were the Reaſons that mov'd me to engage my ſelf in this Controverſy. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I have detected the Doctor's Errors, and defended the Truth as I ought, I leave the Reader to judg. God be thanked, we have a Prince, who wants not courage to defend his Legal Right with his Sword; and I believe he will never want Writer's to juſtify it with their Pens; and to prove that neither was he an Uſurper, not were they that aſſiſted him, Rebels.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
